Armenfilm studio production
Production by Armenfilm Studio
after Hamo Beknazarian
THE MEN
Screenplay by Edmond Keosayan
and Alexander Chervinkiy
Producer
Edmond Keosayan
Director of Photography
Nikolay Vasipkov
Production Designer
Rafael Babayan
Original Score by
Robert Amirkhanyan
Starring
Armen Dzhigarkhanyan as Ghazaryan
Mher Mkrtchyan as Souren
Azat Sherents as Vazgen
Avetik Geyorgyan as Aram
Armen Ayvazyan as Sako
Alla Tumanyan as Karine
Cast
L. Keosayan as Ghazaryan's wife
Многодетный — В. ПОДПОМОГОВ
V. Podpomogov as the father of many daughters
S. Potikyan as the policeman
R. Kotanjyan as Levon
K. Khandanyan as Anoush
Arthur Sahakyan as Samvel
As you can guess,
if a movie is called "The Men"
then, the main character,
naturally, would be a woman.
However, let's not rush the story.
The movie is called "The Men",
and one cannot ignore that.
There are many men in Armenia,
and today that is not a secret anymore.
We will tell you about only four of them.
So, the first one is Vazgen.
Vazgen never confines himself
to merely his own interests.
Whatever dispute takes place in the city,
his is the last word,
because the wisdom and
the integrity of that man
is directly proportional to the respect
Vazgen has earned among all the strata
of the urban population.
"Let me think" Vazgen says.
You have to agree that is
surprisingly simple and wise.
And everybody around
suddenly feels at ease.
Sako.
He is not a painter.
But he understands life.
Clearly, the longing
for beauty inhabited
the most hidden corners of his
sophisticated soul for too long
and only now bursted out
with some violent force.
And if now sometimes Sako
finds himself walking on streets
not very well-lit
trust me, it is only so he can
once again realize how far
he is from all of that.
True, some, who encounters him,
are startled for a second.
But it's only for a second.
The entire city knows that
Sako has a will of steel.
Suren.
Suren jan.
With all due sympathy
to that man
one hardly can call him wise,
in fact, that would be impossible.
City folk might say that
he has air in his head,
and to a certain degree
that is a fair assessment.
This is a cake.
Not just a cake.
This cake is made in a factory,
which for many years
was run by Suren's
younger brother Romeo.
This is Romeo's wife Medea.
And this is their son Hamlet.
This is Souren's mom.
At first glance, everything
in her life seems ideal.
But that is not so.
The fact that Suren is still a bachelor
taints the taste of the cake
and the sound of the music.
This is Souren's grandfather Hamazasp.
They say, he was the first
to drive a car in our city.
They say, Souren's father Vardan
made it to Berlin with his lorry,
and on one of the front-line roads,
he picked up Marshal Baghramyan.
They say.
Grandma Vartanush knows very well
why Souren has air in his head.
In fact, he is the only one
who doesn't know.
The youngest of the four men,
who came to our city,
is a distance learning student
at the Agricultural Institute.
Aram.
Aram works in
the 3rd taxi parking lot,
Where he has found connection,
true friendship,
and even protection
of the other three men.
Pay attention to that glance.
It is not innate,
it has been acquired
more or less recently.
The first overwhelming emotion
that befell Aram,
has made his glance that way.
Karine, the daughter of a well-respected
scientist Smbad Kalashyan,
did not have the faintest idea.
Of all the exemplary
qualities of a real man,
Aram possesses the most noble,
he is not talkative.
There existed too many incredible
situations in his imagination,
where he might have become
acquainted with Karine.
But none of them were
meant to arise.
This ancient dance
is called kochari.
It's main characteristic is that
only men dance it.
Women are occupied with housework.
So, men dance it
hands locked tightly,
huddled shoulder to shoulder.
Kochari will denote
a new chapter in our story.
He is called by the common
Armenian name Levon.
These are Levon's watches.
Not only they tell time, date,
the day of the week, month, and year,
but also the average
temperature on the Solaris,
and most importantly, the direction
and the speed of drifting icebergs.
Levon's job is difficult
and responsible.
The difficulty lies in that
he must always pretend
to derive immense pleasure from
the nauseating curiosity of tourists.
The responsibility of his job lies in that
he has no right to forget,
not even for a minute,
that in front of him is a distant West,
behind him native Armenia.
What else?
Oh yes, to our story Levon
has almost no connection,
which gives us the right to resolutely
return to our protagonists,
who today work for Intourist.
В маршруте этой группы улица,
по которой мы едем, не значилась.
The road we drive now
is not on the group's route.
It's Vazgen's personal initiative.
He wise thoughts churned over
the unsolved problem
of his young colleague.
Yes, this is the house
Karine lives in.
Here is some news.
Turns out, they know each other.
Sergeant Sahakyan, in fact,
as all traffic police in the city,
is not only an excellent professional,
but well educated person.
Have you heard?
We are still going to have to deal
with Karine's little brother.
The dentist Ghazaryan himself
and his wife don't have the faintest idea
about the wonderful
surprises awaiting them.
It seems,
that Vazgen's bright mind came up
with something of a salvation.
I feel like
he is about to pronounce
his famous "let me think,"
which means that everything
has been thought of already.
And there it is.
Turns out there is
a simple solution.
You need to do what Vazgen's
father did in his own time, propose.
Aram has no father.
But he has a mother.
She will go to Kalashyan.
It's like this, Smbat Arakelovich,
Here is my Aram, here is your Karine,
let's become in-laws.
With that in mind they went to
Ashtarak, the hometown of Aram.
This is Anoush, Aram's neighbor.
How quickly they grow,
the neighborhood girls.
Aram's mother.
This is grandma Nenek.
She is baking lavash.
Anoush's brother is called James.
As you can see, name trends
found their way to this place too.
Have you ever had a chance
to sit at a Caucasian table?
Not yet?
It means you are yet
to experience the awe
of your own merits, the ones
you did not even suspect you had..
A true toastmaster will make sure
to point out the most hidden
and most beautiful parts
of your soul.
Despite having just met you
for the first time.
And although glasses are full
with excellent grape wine,
a lot more will be spoken
than drunk at the table.
Maybe that is why there are
no detox centers in Armenia.
Who knows.
Сейчас, мне кажется, Вазген
найдет самую подходящую минуту,
I feel like now Vazgen
will find the right moment,
ЧТОбЫ ИЗЛОЖИТЬ маме Арама
to present to Aram's mother
ВСЮ значительность
надвигающихся СОбЫТИЙ.
the entire importance
of the upcoming events.
Ануш, сядь рядом с Арамом.
Anoush, take a sit next to Aram.
Стойте, стойте,
что же это получается?
Wait, what's happening?
Оказывается, У мамы
на ЭТОТ счет СВОИ ВИДЫ.
Turns out the mother has
her own ideas on that matter.
Согласитесь, такого обстоятельства
Вазген предвидеть не МОГ.
You have to agree, Vazgen
couldn't have predicted that.
Ай-ай-ай!
Tut-tut!
Однако отказаться ОТ идеи
сватовства Вазген не МОГ,
However, Vazgen couldn't abandon
the idea of matchmaking,
так КаК Арам НИ О КОМ, кроме
Карине, И слушать не хотел.
since Aram didn't want to even hear
about anybody other than Karine.
Безвыходных ситуаций
для Вазгена не существует.
There are no impossible
situations for Vazgen.
Сватать будет дядя.
The uncle will ask for marriage.
дядей назначен Сурен.
Souren is appointed as the uncle.
Калашьян.
Kalashyan.
— Здравствуйте.
Hello.
Вы Калашьян?
Are you Kalashyan?
— да, но…
— Это вам.
Yes, but…
This is for you.
Не понимаю.
I don't understand.
Здесь фотодокументы.
Here are the photo documents.
Мне НеОбХОДИМО ГОВОРИТЬ
С вами тет-а-тет.
I need to speak to you
tête-à-tête.
Прошу, пожалуйста.
Come in, please.
Благодарю.
Thank you.
Ничего не понимаю.
I don't understand anything.
— Товарищ...
— Меня зовут Сурен.
Comrade…
My name is Souren.
Сурен умеет произвести
впечатление даже на профессора,
Souren can make a good impression
even on a professor,
ХОТЯ ИЗ'ЬЯСНЯТЬСЯ ПО-РУССКИ ему
сложнее, чем на РОДНОМ языке.
although for him Russian is much harder
than his native language.
Очень приятно.
Pleased to meet you.
О, как у вас здесь
очень даже хорошо!
Oh, what a nice place
you got here!
— Садитесь.
— Спасибо, и вы садитесь.
Take a sit.
Thank you, you too, please.
да, я сказал,
что здесь фотодокументы.
Oh yes, I told you,
here are the photo documents.
Вот смотрите, за Вазгеном
стоит мой племянник Арам.
Look, here behind Vazgen
stands my nephew Aram.
Понимаю, Арам.
I understand, that's Aram.
А здесь написано:
"На память Карине от Арама".
And here it says,
"For Karine from Aram."
Понимаю, от Арама.
I understand, it's from Aram.
Арам никого так не любит,
как вашу дочь.
Aram loves your daughter
like nobody else.
Человек он скромный,
среднего роста.
He is a humble man
of an average height.
Среднего?
Любопытно.
Average?
How curious.
УЧ ИТСЯ В И нституте.
He studies at the institute.
— А кто родители?
— Из деревни.
Who are the parents?
Villagers.
думаю, что…
I think that...
ВЫ не знаете СЭГОДНЯШНеЙ деревни.
You don't know today's village.
В конце концов, какая разница,
откуда родом его родители?
After all, what difference does it make
where his parents are from?
Учтите, Арам способен на всё!
Раз, два, три, четыре, пять и — кх!
Consider, Aram is desparate!
One, two, three, four, five and bang!
Нет человека.
Вас будет мучить совесть всю жизнь.
He is gone.
The guilt will torment you for a life.
Я отсюда никуда не уйду,
пока вы не дадите свое согласие.
I won't leave anywhere until
you give your blessing.
Никуда.
Nowhere.
да, он мой племянник.
Но он рос без отца.
True, he is my nephew.
But he grew up without a father.
Я ему был и отцом,
и братом, и дядей, И дРУГОм.
I was a father, a brother, an uncle
and a friend to him.
Ну, что ж, рад был
с вами познакомиться.
Well, it was a pleasure to meet you.
Я тоже.
Likewise.
Извините, я переоденусь.
Располагайтесь.
Excuse me while I change.
Make yourself comfortable.
Очень МИЛЫЙ человек.
Such a nice man.
Извините, дорогой Сурен,
я немного задержался.
I apologize, dear Souren,
it took me a while.
Садитесь, садитесь.
Here, take a sit.
Столько близнецов
под одной крышей.
So many twins
under one roof.
да, профессура —
это всё же профессура.
Professoriate is professoriate.
professorship?
— Ваше здоровье.
— Спасибо.
Your health.
Thank you.
— Угощайтесь.
— Угощаюсь.
Help yourself.
I am helping myself.
— Пожалуйста.
— Спасибо.
Please.
Thank you.
Скоро Карине придет.
Karine will be here soon.
Это хорошо.
That's good.
Очень хорошо.
Very good.
Моя старшая дочь дездемона.
My older daughter Desdemona.
Удивление Сурена
настолько искренне,
Souren's surprise is so sincere,
что он незаметно для себя
перешел на армянский.
that he
Эта Карине тоже хороша.
This Karine is good too.
И на его, Сурена, вкус,
может, даже лучше той.
And to Souren's taste, maybe
even better than the other.
Ох, если бы не упрямство
этого Арама!
Oh, if only Aram was not so stubborn.
Об отступлении
не могло быть и речи.
Ай-ай-ай!
Вазген уже был близок к тому,
чтобы отказаться от этого дела.
Vazgen was so close
to abandon the case.
Но во взгляде Арама
было столько мольбы и надежды!
But there was so much plea
and hope in Aram's glance.
И Арам понял, что Вазгена
осенила новая идея.
And Aram understood that
Vazgen had a new idea.
Идея проста, не правда ли?
Is it a simple idea, is it not?
Итак, приступим к ее реализации.
So , let's get to the implementation.
ВСё складывается
КаК нельзя лучше.
Things are going
just as planned.
Снимай табличку, Арам, быстро.
Get rid of the … Aram, quick.
Ну, отвечай: "да, я свободен".
Come on, answer her, "Yes, I am free."
Арам!
Aram!
Что же ты молчишь, Арам?
Why are you silent, Aram?
Арам!
Aram!
Нет, ЭТО НеПОСТИЖИМО.
This is unbelievable.
Ай-ай-ай!
Было бы заблуждением считать,
It would be a mistake to assume
будто наши мужчины
никогда не расставались.
that our men never parted.
Во-первых, их разлучали пассажиры,
First of all, they parted their ways
because of passangers,
которые указывали
самые разные маршруты.
who specified
very different routes.
Потом, у каждого были
и свои заботы. Всё это так.
Then, everybody had their own life.
All that is true.
Но друзья никогда не упускали
случая быть вместе.
But the friends never missed
a chance to be together.
А СТОИЛО ИМ ТОЛЬКО СОбРаТЬСЯ,
And everytime they gathered
КаК ВНОВЬ возникала неотложная
задача — КаК ПОМОЧЬ Араму.
the pressing issue on how to help
Aram would arise.
действительно, придумано здорово.
Indeed, a great idea.
Вариант беспроигрышный.
Но даже ради друга Сако
не соглашался на роль хулигана.
But even for the friend's sake Sako
couldn't agree to the hooligan's role.
Это, в общем, понятно.
All in all, it is understandable.
Сурен готов
на что угодно, однако…
Souren is ready for anything, though...
Это тоже, в общем, понятно.
That too is understandable.
Да…
Yes..
Свистеть, к сожалению,
Вазген не умел.
Unfortunately, Vazgen did not
know how to whistle.
Карине, К сожалению, не испугалась.
Karine, unfortunately, did not get scared.
Малыш не заплакал.
The kid did not cry.
Бежать ей трудно.
It is hard for her to run.
Вазгену тоже, у него
неважная кардиограмма.
It is hard for Vazgen too,
his cardiogram is poor.
Повышенная душевная
возбудимость влюбленного
Increased mental sensitivity
тоже не была учтена Вазгеном.
wasn't considered by Vazgen either.
"Окмяцек" — это
по-армянски "помогите".
"Ognetsek" is "help" in Armenian.
Ай-ай-ай!
"Ес кес сирумем" —
по-армянски "я люблю тебя".
"Yes kez sirum em" is
"I love you" in Armenian.
НИ О каком сватовстве, знакомстве,
ни о какой взаимности
Арам уже и не мечтал.
Aram could not dream anymore.
СКРаСИТЬ его существование могла
ЛИШЬ ВОЗМОЖНОСТЬ видеть Карине.
Only the possibility of seeing Karine
could brighten up his existence.
Видеть?
Неужели и это невозможно?
Seeing her?
Is that not possible either?
Подумать надо.
Let me think.
дальнейшая картина
представлялась Вазгену
The picture Vazgen
saw in his mind
совершенно ЯСНОЙ.
was absolutely clear.
Карине непременно заметит
ЭТОТ печальный ВЗГЛЯД.
Karine will definitely notice
this sad glance.
Заметит.
She will.
А УЖ когда заметит,
обязательно оценит.
And when she notices it,
she will definitely appreciate it.
Но как поселить Арама
в квартире зубного врача?
But how to… Aram
in the dentist's apartment?
для Вазгена это, конечно,
не представляло особого труда.
For Vazgen,of course,
that was not too difficult.
Расчет Вазгена
был просто и безошибочен.
Vazgen's calculation was plain
and unmistakable.
Какой армянин не окажет
гостеприимства тому,
No Armenian will fail to offer
hospitality to anybody,
КТО назвался РОДСТВеН Н И КОМ?
who called oneself a relative.
Скоро придет жена.
The wife will come home soon.
БЫТЬ может, ЭТО ее РОДСТВеННИКИ?
Maybe they are her relatives?
Пришла жена.
The wife came.
Она честно пыталась
узнать ЭТИХ РОДСТВеННИКОВ.
She tried hard to
recognize these relatives.
Нет.
No.
Не знает.
She doesn't know them.
Не помнит.
Нет.
She doesn't remember.
No.
РаЗГОВОР не очень клеился,
а молчание СТаНОВИЛОСЬ ТЯГОСТНЫМ.
Всего хорошего,
молодой человек.
All the best, young man.
Спасибо за всё, дядя,
за всё спасибо.
Thanks for everything, uncle.
Thank you.
Не грусти, брат,
у дяди тебе будет хорошо.
Do not be sad, brother.
The uncle will take good care of you.
до свидания, тетя.
Farewell, aunty.
Тронут, очень тронут.
I am touched, very touched.
Я всё расскажу маме.
I will tell mom everything.
до поздней ночи супруги
листали семейные альбомы,
Till late at night, the couple
Looked through the family albums,
пытаясь ОТЬ|СКаТЬ ЭТО звено
trying to find the missing link
в бесконечной цепи
фамильного родства.
in the endless chain of family members.
Безуспешно.
To no avail.
Неужели нельзя сушить белье
где-нибудь в другом месте?
Why can't they dry the laundry
somewhere else?
Как хорошо,
что я встретил тебя, Сурен.
It's wonderful I met you here, Souren.
Поздравь меня, друг, я женюсь.
Congratulate me, my friend,
I am getting married.
Только не спрашивай,
кто она, откуда, не спрашивай.
Don't ask me who she is,
where she is from, don't.
Это не девушка, это легенда!
She is not a girl, she is a legend!
Вазген!
дорогои мои Вазген, иди к нам.
Vazgen! My dear Vazgen, come join us.
Не спрашивай, кто она.
Не спрашивай.
Don't ask who she is. Just don't.
душа поет.
давайте петь вместе.
My soul sings, let's sing together.
Только тихо, не надо будить город.
Sing quietly, no need to wake up the city.
Сако-джан!
Поздравь меня, я женюсь.
Sako jan! Congratulate me,
I am getting married.
ТОЛЬКО не спрашивай, КТО она.
Don't ask who she is.
А теперь ПРИГОТОВЬТеСЬ К самому
печальному месту В нашем рассказе.
Now embrace yourself for
the saddest part in our story.
Вы помните Левона?
Ну, того, гида?
Do you remember Levon?
Левона, который к нашей истории
почти никакого отношения не имеет?
That guide who had almost
no connection to our story?
Наутро, конечно, выпал снег.
Of course, the next morning,
it snowed.
Такого раннего снега
СТаРОЖИЛЫ не ПОМНЯТ.
The old-timers couldn't remember
snow that fell so early.
Синоптики, как водится,
объясняли это редкое явление
Forecasters, as usual,
explained this rare phenomenon
ЦИКЛОНаМИ И антициклонами,
with cyclones and anticyclones,
СТОЛКНОВеНИЯМИ ХОЛОДНЫХ И теплых
масс где-то над морем Лаптевых.
the collision of cold and warm air masses
somewhere over the Laptev Sea.
НО МЫ-ТО С вами знаем,
отчего снег выпал именно СЭГОДНЯ.
But you and I know why
it snowed today.
Арам, ну как?
Aram, how are you?
Всё хорошо, Арам?
Are you okay, Aram?
Сегодня ОН не МОГ
ИМ сказать правды.
Today he could not
tell them the truth.
СТОЛЬКО сделали ОНИ ДЛЯ него.
They have done
so much for him.
Конец
The end